Mary Bachman Antique Comb Collection
Mary Bachman Antique Comb Collection
1850-1969
Bachman, Mary.
3 linear ft.
Hair combs, decorative and functional, dating from the mid-19th to mid-20th century.
5201228
Biographical History
Mary Bachman is a member of the Antique Comb Collectors Club and editor of their newsletter. She is also the author of Collector's Guide to Hair Combs: Identification and Values (1998).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mary Bachman Antique Comb Collection consists of 21 combs and hairpins. Most were made in the United States, but the collection also includes a few from France, England, China, and Indonesia. Materials include brass, silver, horn, ivory, and celluloid. Most are hand-made, and date from 1850-1969 although one undated item, from China, may be considerably older.
Identification numbers and descriptions in the inventory below are taken from supplemental information provided by Glenn Beall (see files).
Arrangement of the Collection
No particular order.
Related Material
See also the
Mary Bachman Papers
. has several other collections related to hair combs, as well as a considerable amount of material related to plastics history and production generally. Please to locate other collections related to plastics and industrial design, and refer to to locate cataloged publications. Please also visit the Plastics Collection Website.
Separated Material
A copy of Mary Bachman's book, Collector's Guide to Hair Combs: Identification & Values (1988) has been sent to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
Subject and Genre Headings
Plastics; Bachman, Mary.; Combs -- History.; Combs -- Specimens.; Hair ornaments.; Combs (hair ornaments)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Three of the items (002, 007, and 020) are broken. Exercise extreme care in handling, so as not to lose pieces or cause further damage.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mary Bachman, 2019.
Inventory
- Combs
  - High back comb, 1890-1920; bachman_m_001; American?, celluloid, openwork, hand-cut (Oversize 1)
  - High back comb, 1850-1920; bachman_m_003; Chinese, ivory, openwork with dragons, hand-cut (Oversize 1)
  - High back comb, 1810-1910; bachman_m_004; American?, celluloid, openwork with blue and green rhinestones, hand-cut (Oversize 1)
  - Low back comb, 1810-1950; bachman_m_006; injection molded comb with cut steel header; comb is likely not the original one (Oversize 1)
  - Three-tooth hair pin, 1890-1910; bachman_m_013; clarified horn teeth with gilded filigree brass header (Oversize 1)
  - High back comb, 1890-1910; bachman_m_005; stainless steel, sheared and embossed (Oversize 2)
  - Small low back comb, 1890-1910; bachman_m_009; American?, cow horn with paint and gilt accents, handmade (Oversize 2)
  - Two-tooth hair pin, 1960s; bachman_m_010; French?, celluloid acetate injection molded teeth, decorated with gilt leaves, beads, seed pearls, rhinestones (Oversize 2)
  - Two-tooth hair pin, 1960s; bachman_m_011; American, polystyrene injection molded teeth, decorated with gilt leaves and rhinestones (Oversize 2)
  - Two-tooth hair pin, bachman_m_012; French, polystyrene injection molded teeth colored to resemble tortoiseshell, decorated with rhinestone, beads, polystyrene flowers (Oversize 2)
  - Two-tooth hair pin, 1920; bachman_m_014; steel wire teeth, Art Deco style celluloid header decorated with rhinestones and paint (Oversize 2)
  - Two-tooth hair pin, 1920-1940; bachman_m_015; injection-molded polystyrene teeth, purple and maroon Art Deco style header (Oversize 2)
  - Single-tooth bodkin, unknown; bachman_m_016; Chinese, brass tooth, brass header with kingfisher feathers (only a few remain) and carved brown jade design (Oversize 2)
  - Case comb, 1890-1915; bachman_m_018; silver case and back decorated with hand chasing, celluloid teeth colored to resemble tortoiseshell (Oversize 2)
  - Five-tooth comb, [1925?]; bachman_m_019; novelty comb with lion's head, likely injection molded and then chrome-plated (Oversize 2)
  - High back comb, 1900-1930; bachman_m_002; American?, celluloid, openwork with blue and green rhinestones, hand-cut (Oversize 3)
    Broken. Exercise extreme care in handling, so as not to lose pieces or cause further damage.
  - Low back comb, mid-1800s; bachman_m_007; British?, horn with faceted jet accents, handmade (Oversize 3)
  - Low back comb, mid-1800s; bachman_m_008; British?, wire frame with faceted jet accents (Oversize 3)
  - Folding case comb, bachman_m_017; Chinese, silver case, silver comb with rods individually set (Oversize 3)
  - Grooming comb, bachman_m_020; Sumatran, cast brass header with Islamic filigree work, clarified horn teeth colored to resemble tortoiseshell (Oversize 3)
  - High back comb, 1850-1890; bachman_m_021; American?, horn, two pieces attached with small glass rivets (Oversize 3)